I was born and raised in Sierra Leone,
ولدت ونشأت في سيراليون
a small and very beautiful country
دولة صغيرة وجميلة جدًا
in West Africa,
في غرب أفريقيا ،
a country rich both in physical resources
بلد تزخر بالموارد المادية
and creative talent.
والمواهب الإبداعية .
However, Sierra Leone is infamous
ومع ذلك، فقد ساءت سمعتها
for a decade-long rebel war in the '90s
بحرب المتمردين التي استمرت عقد كامل في التسعينات
when entire villages were burnt down.
عندما تم حرق قرى بأكملها .
An estimated 8,000 men, women and children
وحوالي 8000 رجل وامرأة وطفل
had their arms and legs amputated during this time.
تم بتر أذرعتهم وأرجلهم أثناء ذلك الوقت.
As my family and I ran for safety
عندما هربت مع عائلتي من أجل سلامتنا
when I was about 12 from one of those attacks,
من احد تلك الهجمات ، كان عمري حوالي 12 عامًا ،
I resolved that I would do everything I could
عزمت على أن أفعل كل ما في مقدرتي
to ensure that my own children
لضمان أن أطفالي
would not go through the same experiences we had.
لن يمروا بالتجارب نفسها التي مررنا بها.
They would, in fact, be part of a Sierra Leone
بل سيصبحون ، في الواقع ، جزء من سيراليون
where war and amputation
عندما لا تكون الحرب وبتر الأطراف
were no longer a strategy for gaining power.
استراتيجية للإستيلاء على السلطة .
As I watched people who I knew, loved ones,
أثناء متابعتي لأناس أعرفهم ، وأحبهم ،
recover from this devastation,
يستعيدون عافيتهم من هذا الدمار ،
one thing that deeply troubled me
كان هناك شئ واحد أحزنني بعمق
was that many of the amputees in the country
وهو أن أغلب مبتوري الأطراف في الدولة
would not use their prostheses.
لم يكونوا يستخدمون أطرافهم الأصطناعية .
The reason, I would come to find out,
والسبب ، الذي حاولت أن أجده
was that their prosthetic sockets
كان أن محاجر الأطراف الاصطناعية
were painful because they did not fit well.
كانت تؤلم لأنها لا تناسب الأطرافهم المبتورة .
The prosthetic socket is the part
محجر الطرف الاصطناعي هو ذلك الجزء
in which the amputee inserts their residual limb,
الذي يضع فيه الشخص ما تبقى من طرفه المبتور فيه ،
and which connects to the prosthetic ankle.
والذي يربطه بالكاحل الاصطناعي .
Even in the developed world,
حتى في دول العالم المتقدم ،
it takes a period of three weeks to often years
يستغرق الأمر من 3 أسابيع إلى عدة سنوات
for a patient to get a comfortable socket, if ever.
ليحصل المريض على محجر مريح ، اذا لم يكن إلى الأبد .
Prosthetists still use conventional processes
أخصائيي الأطراف الاصطناعية مازالوا يستخدمون عمليات تقليدية
like molding and casting
مثل القولبة والصب
to create single-material prosthetic sockets.
لصناعة محجر اصطناعي من مادة واحدة .
Such sockets often leave intolerable amounts
ومثل هذه المحاجر تسبب كمية لا تحتمل
of pressure on the limbs of the patient,
من الضغط على أطراف المريض ،
leaving them with pressure sores and blisters.
مخلفةً تقرحات جلدية .
It does not matter
لا يهم
how powerful your prosthetic ankle is.
مدى قوة كاحلك الاصطناعي .
If your prosthetic socket is uncomfortable,
اذا كان محجره غير مريح ،
you will not use your leg,
فلن تستخدم رجلك ،
and that is just simply unacceptable in our age.
وذلك بكل بساطة غير مقبول في عصرنا هذا .
So one day, when I met professor Hugh Herr
في اليوم الذي ألتقيت فيه البروفيسور هيو هير
about two and a half years ago,
قبل حوالي السنتين والنصف ،
and he asked me if I knew how to solve this problem,
سألني اذا ماكنت قد وجدت حلاً لهذه المشكلة ،
I said, "No, not yet,
فقلت ، " لا ، ليس بعد ،
but I would love to figure it out."
لكن يسعدني جداً محاولة ذلك . "
quickly and cheaply
بسرعة وبثمن رخيص
that are more comfortable
وأكثر راحة من الأطراف الاصطناعية التقليدية .
I used magnetic resonance imaging
استخدمت أشعة رنين مغناطيسي
to capture the actual shape of the patient's anatomy,
لألتقط الشكل الحقيقي لأطراف المريض ،
the internal stresses and strains
بالضغط الداخلي والجهد
on the normal forces,
على القوى العادية ،
and then create a prosthetic socket for manufacture.
ثم صممت محجر اصطناعي للتصنيع .
We use a 3D printer to create
استخدمنا طابعات ثلاثية الأبعاد
which relieves pressure where needed
يخفف الضغط على بعض المناطق عند الحاجة
on the anatomy of the patient.
على حسب تفاصيل أطراف المرضى .
In short, we're using data
باختصار ، استخدمنا بيانات
In a recent trial we just wrapped up
في تجربة حديثة غطينا
at the Media Lab,
في مختبرنا ،
one of our patients, a U.S. veteran
حالة أحد المرضى ، جندي أمريكي
who has been an amputee for about 20 years
مبتور الطرف من حوالي 20 سنة
and worn dozens of legs,
وقد جرب عشرات الأطراف الاصطناعية ،
said of one of our printed parts,
قال عن أحد أطرافنا الاصطناعية المطبوعة ،
"It's so soft, it's like walking on pillows,
" إنها طرية ، كما لو أنني أمشي على وسادة ،
and it's effing sexy."
وأيضاً جذابة للغاية ."
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Disability in our age
الإعاقة في عصرنا
should not prevent anyone
يفترض أن لا تمنع أحداً
My hope and desire is that the tools and processes
أملي ورغبتي أن الأدوات والعمليات
we develop in our research group
التي طورناها في مجموعة الأبحاث
can be used to bring highly functional prostheses
يستفاد منها في توفير أطراف اصطناعية عملية
to those who need them.
لأولائك الذين يحتاجون إليها .
For me, a place to begin healing the souls
بالنسبة لي
of those affected by war and disease
أولائك المصابين بالحرب والمرض
is by creating comfortable and affordable interfaces
هي بإنتاج واجهات مريحة و بأسعار معقولة لأجسادهم
Whether it's in Sierra Leone or in Boston,
سواء كان ذلك في سراليون أو في بوسطون ،
I hope this not only restores
آمل أن لا يكون ذلك مجرد ترميم
but indeed transforms their sense of human potential.
ولكن تحوّل أكيد لشعورهم بقدرتهم البشرية .
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم .